Welcome back. Today's דף daf is מ"ו, mem vav, 47. We pick
up, we're a little behind, we pick up in the middle of
מ"ה עמוד ב mem hei amud bet with תנו רבנן.
tanu
rabbanan. It is five, eight, eleven lines from the bottom, line starts
with the word
לפנים מזה מהו תקח. lifnim mizeh mahu tikach. So we've been talking
about חמץ chametz stuck into the cracks of a vessel and a
kneading trough and at what stage it's insignificant enough and if it's
so and or if it's strengthening the vessel, does it become part
of the vessel and not treated as חמץ chametz and that you
have don't have to get rid of it anymore. And now we
talk about an issue that is has a much more broader application,
which is how edible the thing is. We had discussed a whole
category of חמץ נוקשה, chametz nuksha, which רש"י Rashi said meant not
really fit for eating, and at the stage I said, well, maybe
it's fit for a dog and not for a human, and that
relates to this גמרא Gemara that we are about to see, which
is so central to discussions around medicines and things of the sort
of that sort. So, תנו רבנן: tanu rabbanan: הפת שעיפשה ונפסלה מלאכול
לאדם והכלב יכול לאוכלה, hapat she'ipsha venifsela me'achol la'adam vehakelev yakhol le'okhla,
bread that became moldy, ונפסלה מלאכול לאדם, venifsela me'achol la'adam, can no
longer be eaten by humans, והכלב יכול לאוכלה, vehakelev yakhol le'okhla, but
is still edible by dogs, מטמאה טומאת אוכלין בכביצה. metamma tum'at ochlin
kibeitza. If there is a ביצה beitza worth of it, an egg's
worth, then it can become טמא tamei as טומאה tum'ah of foodstuff.
There's actually debate whether you need the size of a ביצה beitza
for to receive טומאה tum'ah or for to transfer the טומאה, tum'ah,
but nevertheless, the point is it's considered food for the purposes of
foodstuff. ונסרפת. venisrepet. Now I want to make a point which is
an important principle, which is I sometimes tell my students I call
it the stickiness factor, or you could there's a better word for
that I'm sure, but anyway, which basically is that things retain, things
don't give up their status so easily once they get it. It's
easier like it's easier not to hire someone for a job than
to fire them once you've hired them. So once something has a
status, it doesn't lose it so easily, and even if there's some
remnant of its original state left, it still holds on to its
status. So actually, it could be that if something was never fit
for human consumption, it's never considered food and it does not cannot
become טמא tamei as foodstuff. But if it was fit for human
consumption, it won't lose that status as long as it is somewhat
edible, even edible by a dog, and it'll only lose that status
when it comes completely inedible, even inedible
to
a dog. So that is defined as food for the purpose of
טומאת אוכלין. tum'at ochlin. ונסרפת
עם הטמאה בפסח. venisrepet im hatmeiah bePesach. Now let's say that this
is תרומה, terumah, thank you, therefore you can go ahead and burn
this even with תרומה טמאה terumah tmeiah on פסח. Pesach. Normally you
can't burn תרומה טהורה terumah tehorah with טמאה, tmeiah, you're making the
תרומה טהורה טמאה, terumah tehorah tmeiah, but because this is no longer
fit for being eaten, then there is no problem of making it
טמא tamei and of burning it together with the תרומה טמאה. terumah
tmeiah. Okay, so let's take a look. Now ונסרפת עם הטמאה בפסח.
venisrepet im hatmeiah bePesach. משום רב נתן אמרו, mishum Rav Natan amru,
in the name of רב נתן Rav Natan they said, אינה
מטמאה. einah metamma.
Wait
a minute, hold on,
let
me just check one thing in רש"י, Rashi, one second. Okay, fine.
משום רב נתן אמרו אינה מטמאה. mishum Rav Natan amru einah metamma.
Oh no no no, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I jumped
ahead. Okay, I was saying that it was talking, okay, let's do
this one more time because I was in my head already talking
about the case that it's not edible by a dog. Let's read
it one more time. הפת שעיפשה ונפסלה מלאכול לאדם והכלב יכול לאוכלה.
hapat she'ipsha venifsela me'achol la'adam vehakelev yakhol le'okhla.
Okay, I was already jumping to רב נתן. Rav Natan. Okay, so
this is so it's still edible by a dog, and as I
said, because it was once edible by humans, if it's still edible
by a dog, it's still considered food as long as it is
still somewhat edible. So therefore מטמאה טומאת אוכלין בכביצה, metamma tum'at ochlin
kibeitza, it still is food that it could become טמא, tamei, but
ונסרפת עם הטמאה בפסח. venisrepet im hatmeiah bePesach. Although it's still food
that it could be although it's still food, nevertheless, since humans won't
eat it, you can go ahead and burn it with the תרומה
טמאה. terumah tmeiah. Okay, so that's a particular leniency even though fundamentally
it still is considered food. And משום רב נתן אמרו, mishum Rav
Natan amru, in the name of רב נתן Rav Natan they said,
אינה מטמאה. einah metamma. According to רב נתן, Rav Natan, once it's
no longer edible by humans, it no longer can become טמא. tamei.
So bracketing the issue about burning it with the תרומה טמאה, terumah
tmeiah, here's a debate of if it's still edible by dogs, is
it still considered to be food or not if it was once
edible by humans? So now the גמרא Gemara says כמאן אזלא הך
דתנן, keman azla hakh detnan, who is it going like that which
we learned in the משנה? Mishnah? כלל אמרו בטהרות, klal amru betaharot,
they said a general principle in the world of טהרות, taharot, of
purities, כל המיוחד לאוכל אדם, kol hamiyuchad le'okhel adam,
anything that is that is designated for human food, לאוכל אדם, le'okhel
adam, טמא, tamei, it remains it can continue to become טמא tamei
until. עד שיפסל מאכול כלב. ad sheyipasel me'achol kelev. It has to
be not only no longer edible by humans, but once it was
once edible by humans, to lose its status, it has to be
not even edible by dogs. So the גמרא Gemara says, כמאן דלא
כרב נתן. Keman delo kerav Noson. That's not like רב נתן Rav
Noson because רב נתן Rav Noson says that it goes by that
once it's not edible by humans, it stops being considered food. And
this becomes the general principle by פסח Pesach which is this very
important which is exactly this: if something was once edible by humans,
no longer has to become inedible even by dogs in order for
it to not be a problem on פסח. Pesach. And the issue
with a lot of these medicines is that a lot of these
medicines or what not are not even edible by
dogs, but there's a position of the ראש Rosh that the ראש
Rosh says if you take something even if it's not edible by
dogs and you actually eat it, so it's not just a question
of owning it, it's a question of actually eating it, your eating
it gives it subjective importance and makes it considered to be like
food. And then that raises the issue of so then can you
ingest medicines because when you ingest the medicines you're now eating it
and you're making it like food. Basically the פוסקים poskim say that's
not a problem because when you eat it as a medicine you're
not eating it as food, you're eating it as a medicine and
it does not even give you the problem that the ראש Rosh
speaks about which is a problem called אחשביה achshavei that you've given
it subjective importance. So therefore the general position is that once something
is not fit for consumption by dogs we rule like the חכמים
Chachamim not like רב נתן, Rav Noson, the stricter position. But so
once it becomes inedible even by dogs though it's not considered food
and it's not a problem to own and if it's medicine or
the like it's not even a problem to eat or if it's
like I don't know sometimes you have stuff like toothpaste well you've
got you also have you also have like shampoo I'll tell the
toothpaste story in a minute but you got shampoo sometimes that has
like beer in it or something like that although that could be
an issue of הנאה hana'ah which is an interesting would you say
אחשביה achshavei by הנאה hana'ah again if it's not edible. But if
it's something that's not done as food, it's not eaten and it's
not fit for אכילת כלב, achilas kelev, that's okay. An interesting question
comes up around vitamins because vitamins or dietary supplements are more like
food than they are and they're not easy to just put into
the medicine category.
So people take it as
medicine though they're not taking it because it tastes good. No, but
people take dietary supplements and so on which is basically to serve
the function of food right. So dietary but it's not
eaten
the way you eat it. So right so vitamins raise an interesting
discussion on פסח. Pesach. I'm just I'm not פוסק poskening for you,
I'm just telling you what the issues are. Anyway so the anyway
but about the dog story I keep on I tell I've told
this story before but they tell the story that the students of
the רב Rav went to him and said you know what's the
story with toothpaste on פסח. Pesach. So he said it's not even
edible by dogs. So they went and they took some toothpaste then
they put it on a paper plate and they went over to
a dog you know those like things in the heights where the
dogs are pretty desperate anyway and the dog like licked it up.
So they went back to the רב Rav and they said you
know the dog ate it. So he said who's your רבי Rebbi
me or the
dog. Anyway all right but this is this principle so when we
speak before about חמץ נוקשה chametz nuksheh not being edible we mean
not being so edible or not being edible by humans but still
edible by dogs but once it's not edible by dogs it's out
of the category.
The examples we had before were also in the same thing
yeah you'd have to say that that those would still be edible
בשעת הדחק. beshas hadechak.
Look some people used to some people used to buy mouthwash alcoholics
and drink it until they've now then they put something in it
so that it makes you throw it up if you try to
drink it so you could have things that are cosmetics that actually
are edible בשעת הדחק beshas hadechak
at least by dogs if not by more.
All right so not now anyway so the גמרא Gemara says like
this תנו רבנן tanu rabanan our rabbis taught עריבת העבדנים. areivas ha'avdanim.
So now we have a similar case of becoming inedible you've got
this type of a trough that you would put that the leather
workers would put their leather in and they would in order to
treat the leather they would have some type of a flower-based sort
of you know mixture there. שנתן לתוכה קמח shenasan letochah kemach
so if you put flour in it for the working the leather
תוך שלשה ימים חייב לבער toch sheloshah yamim chayav leva'er within three
days then the thing is still somewhat potentially edible this solution and
you have to destroy it. קודם שלשה ימים kodem sheloshah yamim it's
more than three days before פסח Pesach אינו חייב לבער eino chayav
leva'er you don't have to because then it stops being edible at
that stage.
Wait what's what were we learning about before when all these things
you have to get in this trough with the חזק chazek it
doesn't mention any of that.
This is a different story this is a solution for working leather.
Oh right. אמר רבי נתן במה דברים אמורים שלא נתן לתוכה עורות
Amar Rabbi Noson bameh devarim amorim shelo nasan letochah oros when is
that true if you haven't actually put the leathers in them. אבל
נתן לתוכה עורות aval nasan letochah oros once you put the leather
in the solution אפילו תוך שלשה אינו חייב לבער afilu toch sheloshah
eino chayav leva'er even within three days you don't have to destroy
it because then the leather completely makes the whole thing inedible. אמר
רבא הלכה כרבי נתן Amar Rava halachah keRabbi Noson we rule like
רב נתן Rav Noson אפילו יום אחד ואפילו שעה אחת afilu yom
echad va'afilu sha'ah achas even if you only put in the leather
a day or an hour before פסח Pesach it totally makes it
inedible. Okay so here you get the very important halachic principle about
once the חמץ chametz becomes inedible it stops being a problem it's
not even חמץ נוקשה chametz nuksheh and the debate whether inedible for
humans or inedible for dogs and we rule the more stronger position
inedible for dogs. certainly if it was once edible for humans. As
I said once it’s edible for humans and gets the full status
of food, it’s harder to lose that and has to become inedible
at least according to the חכמים *Chachamim* even for dogs. Now we
go to the end point of the משנה Mishna *Mishna* about this
dough stuck in the kneading trough where it says the same הלכה
halacha *halacha* applies for טומאה tumah *tumah* whether it is considered to
be part of the trough and is a חציצה chatzitzah, *chatzitza* or
not, is an obstruction or not. וכן לענין טומאה tumah *V'chen l'inyan
tumah*: אם מקפיד עליו חוצץ im makpid alav chotzetz *im makpid alav
chotzetz*, if you are concerned with it, you don’t want it there,
then it is a חציצה chatzitzah, *chatzitza*, it’s an obstruction, ואם רוצה
בקיומו rotzeh b'kiyumo, הרי הוא כעריבה harei hu k'areivah, *v'im rotze b'kiyumov
harei hu k'areiva*, if you want it there it is like the
kneading trough. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, מי דמי *mi dami*,
what do you mean it’s the same story by by by טומאה
tumah *tumah*? התם בשיעורא תליא מילתא *Hasam b'shiura talya milsa*, when you’re
talking about חמץ chametz. *chametz* and פסח Pesach *Pesach*, what determined whether
it was part of the kneading trough or not was the size,
right? Was it a כזית kezayit *kezayis* or not a כזית kezayit.
*kezayis*? And even the other criteria added in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
was is it strengthening the trough or not? But those are objective
criteria of the importance of the dough, the size of it, and
the function it was doing. הכא בקפידא תליא מילתא *Hacha b'kfeida talya
milsa*. For this הלכה halachah *halacha* of טומאה tumah וטהרה *tumah v'tahara*,
for חציצה chatzitzah *chatzitza*, the question is about your subjective קפידא *kfeida*,
your subjective desire for it to be there or not there. That’s
a different criteria. It’s a similar discussion when is it part of
the trough or not, but based on a very different set of
criteria. So אמר רב יהודה *amar Rav Yehuda*: אימא ולענין טומאה אינו
כן *eima u'l'inyan tumah eino kein*. So he says, all right, it
doesn’t mean the same is true by טומאה *tumah*. It means there’s
a different set of criteria by טומאה *tumah*, meaning the same question
of is it part of the trough or not part of the
trough, but based on a different set of criteria, based on the
question of whether you are מקפיד makpid *makpid* or not מקפיד makpid
*makpid*. אמר ליה amar lei אביי *amar lei Abaye*, אביי *Abaye* said
to him, והא וכן לענין טומאה תניא *v'ha v'chen l'inyan tumah tanya*.
You can’t do that. The משנה Mishna *Mishna* says the same is
true by טומאה *tumah*. You can’t change it to say, oh, it
means it’s not—it means something else is true by טומאה *tumah*. אלא
*ella*, although you do know where רב יהודה *Rav Yehuda* is coming
from, it means it’s a similar discussion with a different set of
criteria, but אביי *Abaye* doesn’t buy it. אלא אמר אביי *Ella amar
Abaye*, so אביי *Abaye* says, הכי קאמר *hachi ka'amar*. Here’s how you
read it. וכן לענין צירוף tziruf. טומאה בפסח b'Pesach, *V'chen l'inyan tziruf
tumah b'Pesach*. When it comes to combining stuff for טומאה *tumah* purposes
on פסח Pesach, *Pesach*, meaning whether can you combine—not like we thought
that the issue of טומאה *tumah* was whether the dough becomes part
of the trough and is a חציצה chatzitzah *chatzitza* if you want
to dunk it into the מקוה mikveh. *mikva*, but whether when you—can
you combine the different pieces of dough in the cracks? Let’s take
a look. לענין צירוף טומאה בפסח ובשאר ימות השנה איכא פלוגתא *L'inyan
tziruf tumah b'Pesach u'v'sha'ar yemos hashana ika plugta*. So by פסח Pesach
*Pesach* it would go by the measure of כזית kezayit *kezayis* like
it does by the issue of getting rid of the חמץ chametz
*chametz*, and during the rest of the year it would go by
the—it would be a distinction of whether you were מקפיד makpid, *makpid*
or not מקפיד makpid *makpid*. היכי דמי heichi dami, *Heichi dami*? Now
he's going to spell it out. What's the case? כגון דאיכא פחות
מכביצה אוכלים *K'gon d'ika pachus m'k'beitza ochlim*. Again, the size of an
egg is what’s significant by food. ונגע בהאי בצק v'naga b'hai batzek
בפסח *V'naga b'hai batzek b'Pesach*. Okay, so it touched this dough on
פסח Pesach. *Pesach*. ונגע בהאי בצק *V'naga b'hai batzek*, it touched this
dough that was in the cracks. בפסח *B'Pesach*, if it did this
on פסח Pesach *Pesach*, דאיסורו חשוב de'isuro chashuv *d'issuro chashuv*, then מצטרף
mitztaref, *mitztaref*, because where it’s forbidden, so that gives it significance that
even a כזית kezayit *kezayis* is forbidden. So since a כזית kezayit
*kezayis* has significance, so therefore it—basically what you’ve got is,
you’ve got your kneading trough inside one of the cracks. Here is
a little crack. And here is a little bit of dough inside
one of the cracks. And you’ve got some other stuff going here.
You have an apple over here. You have your apple. Okay. Now
that apple is a small apple. It’s not the size of a
כביצה kebeitza *k'beitza*. Okay, this apple is point nine of a כביצה
*k'beitza*. Now you need a size of a כביצה *k'beitza* for it
to be significant for טומאה *tumah*, to receive טומאה *tumah* to pass
it on. You’ve got this little piece of dough in here and
it’s touching that piece of dough. Is it like that dough is
food and therefore you have the minimum amount of food in one
place and it becomes טמא tamei *tamei*? Or is it like that
dough is part of the kneading trough and it's just like it's
touching the kneading trough and the apple does not become טמא tamei.
*tamei*? Okay, this is the טומאה *tumah* question. Okay? So the question
is, do I consider this food in the crack like it is
food or like it’s part of it? So it says if it’s
פסח Pesach, *Pesach*, then you go by the measure of פסח Pesach
*Pesach*. By פסח Pesach. *Pesach*, if it’s a כזית kezayit *kezayis*, it
has significance, it’s not part of the trough. So therefore, since it’s
happening on פסח Pesach *Pesach*, this is considered separate and it’s considered
there—from the trough and it’s from the vessel, it’s part of this
and it becomes—the apple becomes טמא tamei *tamei*, it’s all combined. If
it’s the rest of the year, the size doesn’t matter, what matters
is do you—are you מקפיד makpid *makpid* or are you not מקפיד
makpid, *makpid*. Okay, so he makes it as a similar criteria as
the כזית kezayit *kezayis* by פסח Pesach *Pesach*, if we’re talking on
פסח Pesach, *Pesach*, we apply a different set of measures. But the
issue is not dunking it in the מקוה mikveh. *mikva* like we
assume when we hear the word חציצה chatzitzah, *chatzitza*. The real issue
is whether it combines with the other food in order for טומאה
*tumah* purposes.
You used an apple because it's not dough, like
if you have—Yeah, I didn't want to start confusing everybody about is
it פסח Pesach *Pesach* and is it also is the dough, is
it also חמץ chametz. *chametz* or not חמץ *chametz*. Okay, I was
just—I was trying to sort of
say
even— So כגון דאיכא פחות מכביצה אוכלין, there's less than a כביצה
food in the
vessel ונגע בהאי בצק and it's touching this dough that's in the
crack. בפסח, it was on פסח Pesach דאיסורו חשוב that even by
a כזית kezayit it's significant because it's forbidden and that's why and
now you would have to get rid of it, right? So it's
on פסח, Pesach this dough in the crack you'd have to get
rid of it because it's a כזית. kezayis, מצטרף, then once it's
a כזית kezayis, that's significant on פסח Pesach and then it becomes
connected with the apple for טומאה purposes. בשאר ימות השנה, bish'ar yemot
hashanah, in the rest of the year, the size doesn't matter. דקפידא
תליא מילתא, dekfida talya milta, then it's about whether you're מקפיד makpid
or not. אי מקפיד עליו מצטרף, im makpid alav mitztaref, if you're
concerned about it, you want to get rid of it, you don't
like it in the crack, then it's considered a separate and it's
considered a food and it combines with the apple.
אם רוצה בקיומו, im rotzeh b'kiyumo, but if you want it to
stay in the crack, הרי הוא כעריבה, harei hu ka'areivah, then it's
like the kneading trough. So we get it to have the same
criteria of a כזית kezayis on פסח. Pesach But conceptually the issue
here is not is it part of the vessel, actually the issue
is opposite, is it a separate unit? Is it food? You might
say it's the flip side of the coin, but what we're trying
to do is actually make it food to combine with something outside
of the vessel itself.
Meaning this thing, is this subject to the same criteria we had
earlier about עשויו לחזק asuyo l'chazeik or not?
טומאה on פסח you mean? No.
Yes, so that's right. The גמרא gemara is bracketing the עשויו לחזק
asuyo l'chazeik and that's a good question. If it's applying the same
criteria on פסח, it might have to combine the כזית kezayis criteria
with the עשויו לחזק asuyo l'chazeik criteria.
The criterion though is subjective. אם רוצה אם אינו רוצה.
im rotzeh im eino rotzeh. Yeah,
during the rest of the year. That's what it's saying. That when
it was talking about פסח it used the objective criteria of כזית
and then the other thing the גמרא gemara threw in was עשויו
לחזק. asuyo l'chazeik.
The משנה Mishna by טומאה talks about מקפיד makpid. or not מקפיד,
רוצה בקיומו, rotzeh b'kiyumo. not רוצה בקיומו. rotzeh b'kiyumo So the first
answer is you would go by the subjective criteria the rest of
the year and the objective criteria on פסח. So מתקיף לה רבא,
matkif lah Rava, רבא Rava asked on this, מי קתני מצטרף? mi
katani mitztaref? The משנה Mishna doesn't say the question is whether it
combines. The משנה Mishna says what's at stake is והחוצץ קתני, v'hachotzetz
katani, that when you don't want it in there, not that it
combines with something else, that's not what's relevant, what the application is.
The application in the משנה Mishna is that the food becomes a
חציצה, chatzitzah. the dough becomes a חציצה, chatzitzah not that it combines
with other food. אלא אמר רבא, ela amar Rava, so רבא Rava
says, וכן להראות טהרה לעריבה. v'chen l'harot taharah l'areivah. So we're talking
like I said to you, the first thing that comes to our
minds when we say חציצה chatzitzah is the issue that you're trying
to purify it and put it in the מקוה. mikveh היכי דמי,
Heichi dami? what's the case? כגון דנטמאת האי עריבה, kegon dentam'at hai
areivah,
so this kneading trough, this vessel became טמא tamei? ובעי למטבליה, v'ba'ei
l'mitbleih, you want to dunk it in the מקוה. mikveh בפסח דאיסורו
חשוב, b'Pesach de'isuro chashuv, by פסח if it has a כזית then
that's significant, חוצץ, chotzetz, the dough is a חציצה chatzitzah? ולא סלקא
ליה טבילה, v'lo salka leih tvilah, the מקוה mikveh. doesn't work, the
טבילה tvilah doesn't work. בשאר ימות השנה דקפידא תליא מילתא, bish'ar yemot
hashanah dekfida talya milta, the rest of the year the size doesn't
matter, what matters is do you want it there or not want
it there. אם מקפיד עליו חוצץ im makpid alav chotzetz, ואי רוצה
בקיומו הרי הוא כעריבה. v'im rotzeh b'kiyumo harei hu k'areivah. If you
want it out of there it's a חציצה, chatzitzah. if you want
it in there it's part of the vessel and it is not
a חציצה. chatzitzah, So that's a very reasonable, I would say the
simplest read of the concern of חציצה chatzitzah, is a מקוה concern.
But because the משנה Mishna compared it to פסח to the criteria
of פסח, he says whether it's considered a חציצה chatzitzah. would depend
whether it's פסח or the rest of the year. So the issue
is not that you've got your apple, the issue is you're putting
your vessel here in your מקוה. Okay, so is this little dough
in here, is that a חציצה? chatzitzah So would you consider it
part of the vessel or not part of the vessel? So because
the משנה Mishna says it's the same הלכה by פסח and by
this, so we say on פסח even once it's a כזית objectively
that's got to come out because it's פסח and it's not part
of the vessel and it's a חציצה. chatzitzah The rest of the
year the size doesn't matter, what matters is do you want it
there or not want it there. If you want it there it's
part of the vessel, not a חציצה, chatzitzah you don't want it
there it is a חציצה, chatzitzah it is an obstruction. Now I
should say and I said this yesterday that this is a very
significant excluded middle in this משנה Mishna which is, the משנה mishnah.
says you know if you right, the משנה mishnah says if you
מקפיד means you want it out of there it's a חציצה. chatzitzah.
If
you רוצה בקיומו rotzeh bekiyumo, then it's part of the vessel. What
about the whole middle case where you don't care if it's there
or not? You don't דוקא davka want it out, you don't דוקא
davka want it in. And that's a very important חציצה chatzitzah. question.
If somebody has something on their you know, you know on their
body or whatnot, do you need to get to a threshold where
you say oh it's not a חציצה chatzitzah because they need it
on their body and they want it on their body, like stitches?
You know let's say because they דוקא davka need it there because
the wound is still healing or whatnot, then it's not a חציצה
chatzitzah? because then it's part of your body. Or is it enough
to say... Say, I don't really care one way or the other,
right? Is that enough? Normally it seems like normally by חציצה chatzitzah.
הלכות halachas the criteria is מקפיד versus אינו מקפיד. eino makpid. Once
you're not מקפיד, once you don't care, as opposed to wanting it
off, once you don't care whether it's there or not, it's not
a problem. But there are some פוסקים poskim that want a higher
threshold, that want to say it's like you דווקא davka want it
there that makes it part of your body and it's not enough
just not to care.
By the way, that could, that could easily apply to a wedding
band.
I don't want to take it off because I will lose it,
I will forget
about it, I will not be calm, I just...
Right, a lot of things that we לכתחילה lechatchilah treat as חציצות
chatzitzas are things that by any measure are not חציצה. It's דווקא
davka you want it there, right? And nevertheless we have a לכתחילה
lechatchilah to remove all obstructions even things that are without a question,
right? Right. So anyway, yes, so all of that is true. Okay,
now the גמרא gemara continues. So that's Rava's answer, very reasonable read
of the משנה. mishnah Let's see what the גמרא gemara's does with
it.
מתקיף לה רב פפא, Matkif lei Rav Pappa, Rav Pappa asked them
this, מי קתני וכן לענין טהרה? mi katani vechen le'inyan taharah? That
would be a very nice read, except the משנה mishnah doesn't say
the same is true by purifying. והא לענין טומאה קתני. Vahale inyan
tumah katani. The משנה mishnah. said the issue is about becoming טמא.
tamei. So he tried to say טמא tamei to combine with the
apple, but then it said that would be about צירוף. This says
חציצה. So where's there an issue that it's about חציצה but not
becoming טהור tahor but becoming טמא? tamei. So let's take a look
how he's going to explain it. אלא אמר רבא אלא אמר רב
פפא, Ella amar Rava ella amar Rav Pappa, וכן לענין להוריד טומאה
לעריבה. vechen le'inyan lehorid tumah la'areivah. The issue is whether this kneading
cloth, this vessel, will become טמא. tamei. היכי דמי? heichi dami, כגון
דנגע שרץ בהאי בצק. Kegon denaga sheretz behai batzek. So it's not
in the מקווה, mikvah, there's no apple, what there is is that
there is a little שרץ sheretz here. Okay, you got a שרץ.
sheretz. Your kitchen got a שרץ. sheretz. Okay, you got your little
שרץ. sheretz. Now this שרץ sheretz did not directly touch the actual
cloth itself. It only touched this little piece of dough that was
in the crack that was sticking out of the cloth. It touched
the dough. Is touching the dough like touching the עריבה areivah or
not? Is it a חציצה? So it's a obstruction, it's not part
of the עריבה, areivah, you don't want it there. It's an obstruction,
it's independent, so it touched the dough and it didn't touch the
עריבה. areivah. Or if you want it there, רוצה בקיומו, then it's
just a part of the עריבה. areivah. Touching the dough is touching
the עריבה. areivah. And that is the issue about where it matters
if you're מקפיד or not מקפיד. And it's about it becoming טמא
because it's about it being part of the עריבה areivah or not
part of the עריבה. areivah.
The שרץ sheretz has to be dead.
Dead, yes.
Okay,
היכי דמי, what's the case? כגון דנגע שרץ בהאי בצק. Kegon denaga
sheretz behai batzek. It touched the dough. בפסח דאיסורו חשיב, BePesach de'issuro
chashiv, by Pesach where the, where the fact that it's forbidden gives
it significance, חוצץ. chotzetz. Even a כזית, it goes by the standards
that you would have to get rid of the חמץ. Once you
have to get rid of it, it's an independent thing, ולא נחתא
ליה טומאה, velo nachtah lei tumah, and the vessel doesn't become טמא.
בשאר ימות השנה, Bish'ar yemos hashanah,
the rest of the year it's not about the size, it's about
whether you want it or not. אם מקפיד עליו חוצץ, if you
want the dough out of there, it's an independent unit and it's
a חציצה. אם רוצה בקיומו im rotzeh bekiyumo and if you want
it there to fill the gap, to make it part of the
vessel, הרי הוא כעריבה, it is like the vessel. So basically, and
therefore it becomes טמא. So basically his position would, maybe they all
agree להלכה, lehalachah, all three opinions agree with one another. Presumably he
would certainly agree with Rava about the מקווה mikvah case. But nevertheless,
his פשט pshat of the משנה mishnah makes it about actual טומאה
and not about טהרה. taharah. Okay, very nice. Moving on to the
next משנה. Mishnah. So we just had a very important גמרא Gemara
about the issue about ראוי לאכילת כלב, ra'ui la'achilas kelev, one very
important standard for defining something, is it still considered חמץ on Pesach?
And I mentioned to you that even the position of the Rosh,
that even when it's no longer ראוי, ra'ui, if you eat it,
that might give it subjective significance. This next משנה Mishnah. introduces, or
in the גמרא discussion, another very critical הלכה for חמץ. Let's take
a look. בצק החרש. Batzek hacherish. So there's a question whether you
pronounce this חרש cheresh or החרש. hacherish. Okay, basically it means that
you've got dough that has really hardened and there is no way
of identifying whether it has fermented because remember, we've always been defining
that you can determine fermentation by observation, by whether it's, you know,
whether it's expanded, whether there are cracks in the surface. Let's say
this stuff has really like hardened and you didn't have a chance
to observe it earlier and you can't see whether it ever reached
the stage of fermentation. So... רש״י *Rashi* says so what is this
word so רש״י *Rashi* wants to say it's חרש *cheresh* because like
a mute person a deaf person that like you can't communicate so
you can't really assess its status. The other explanation probably an easier
one is חרס *cheres* which is like pottery. It's hard like pottery
and therefore you can't assess whether you can't you know whether it
at what whether it actually fermented or not. So how do you
determine it? What? It's not edible? I guess it's edible enough by
a dog. What?
You soak it and it'll soften?
Oh that's true. Okay that's true. You mean to make it edible.
אם יש כיוצא בו *im yesh kayotzei bo* so the משנה *Mishnah*
says שיחמיץ *she-hichmitz* you determine if other bread that has been out
that long as long as this bread has been would have fermented
or did ferment הרי זה אסור *harei zeh assur*. It's forbidden. So
if you can't actually determine by observation what the משנה *Mishnah* is
saying is you determine by by your by you know by your
knowledge about how about other breads and other doughs and how long
it would take them to ferment. And if you know other doughs
that have been out there as long as this normally ferment then
this is a problem. So this is the beginning of the quantification
of the definition of חמץ *chametz* as opposed to we've always assumed
it goes by observation. Here it says when observation isn't possible then
you determine it based on the amount of time it normally takes
dough to ferment. So let's take a look. The גמרא *Gemara* says
אם אין in, שם כיוצא בו מהו *im ein sham kayotzei bo
mahu*. Now let's say you don't have other dough that was made
at the same time right? It's not like oh just observe other
doughs that were made at the time and observe them. Let's say
you don't have those other doughs. So what do you so you
have to go by a general principle of how long it takes
things. So what what do you do then? So אמר רבי אבא
אמר רבי שמעון בן לקיש כדי שיהלך אדם ממגדל נוניא לטבריה מיל
*Amar Rabbi Abba amar Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish kedei she-yeilech adam mi-Migdal
Nunia le-Tverya mil*. Then you go by amount of time. The time
it takes to go from this place מגדל נוניא *Migdal Nunia* to
טבריה *Tverya* which is a מיל *mil*. A מיל *mil* is about
a kilometer. Okay ונימא מיל *ve-neima mil* why not just say a
מיל *mil*? Why do you have to say the time it takes
to walk? הא קמשמע לן *ha ka mashma lan* it's teaching you
דשיעור דמיל כמגדל נוניא לטבריה *de-shiur de-mil ke-Migdal Nunia le-Tverya* that's the
that's if you want to know how long a מיל *mil* is.
So it was before the period of of standardized measurements so now
you know it's the distance. Now based on other גמרות *Gemarot* how
long does it take to walk a מיל *mil*? There's a debate
of ראשונים *Rishonim* whatever different positions in גמרא *Gemara* but generally the
minimum time based on other גמרות *Gemarot* it's assumed that it takes
to walk a מיל *mil* is eighteen minutes. I will tell you
you know normally it seems to me that it takes about twenty
minutes to walk a mile. A mile and a מיל *mil* is
about a point six of a mile it's about a kilometer. Okay
so that would actually be twelve minutes. I don't know. So you
have to assume that we're talking about like a half hour mile.
I mean basically right it takes me twenty minutes to walk a
mile when I'm walking in New York City on paved roads totally
flat. Different people
also walk at different paces.
A pregnant woman is going to right exactly.
And and is it a paved road not paved road is there
an incline? So this assumes about a half hour mile and about
an eighteen minute מיל *mil* an eighteen minute kilometer. That's other גמרות
*Gemarot* that's assumed as the minimum amount of time it takes and
this is where we get the principle that if you leave the
dough outside of the oven without putting it in the oven and
without continuing to work it and you leave it alone for eighteen
minutes then that it will ferment. It is based on the fact
that until now and again it just is an interesting indication of
you know the move of הלכה *Halacha* to quantify because rather than
to leave things to case by case subjective assessments. The entire גמרא
*Gemara* assumes you determine if it's חמץ *chametz* by observation but this
one גמרא *Gemara* says if it's impossible to make the observation you
use an amount of time and for us we've just translated it
straight into a measure of time and nothing else.
But I haven't really seen that based on the way the משנה
*Mishnah*'s describing it first you see חרס *cheres*. Is it going to
get rock hard in eighteen minutes? I mean you know that would
presumably take a lot longer to get rock hard. And then and
even you know חרס *cheres* and even if you say that oh
you can't tell you're never going to be able to tell in
such a little bit amount of time was my point only eighteen
minutes? I mean you know this sounds like they've been out there
for quite a while and you can't tell.
Yeah I don't know. It could be that it became hard I
mean oh you mean it became hard it's been out there a
lot longer
than eighteen minutes it wouldn't become hard?
Yeah I don't know. I don't know how it happened that you're
right I don't know how that happened. But on the other hand
it's not it doesn't make sense to think that something can be
out there for hours right? So I don't know exactly look if
I worked more in the
dough I'd have an answer for you.
Well it's unclear whether אם יש כיוצא בו *im yesh kayotzei bo*
could mean that on a different day and in a different place
like if you know that this is how long this kind of
dough would take to ferment.
Doesn't mean right so if you know that the type of dough
you're working with normally takes twenty-five minutes and then the גמרא *Gemara*
is just saying that if you don't have any basis of comparison
then you use the eighteen minutes right. Right well the question about
how could it have taken so long and still not been חמץ
*chametz* so long that it became hard. Yeah I don't know maybe
it has to do something with the ingredients or whatever doesn't necessarily
mean it's rock hard it means that it's crusted over in a
way that you can no longer the normal things you would look
at are no longer measurable. Does it feel a little bit of
a I don't know do you know how to look at
bread at dough? You put it in the oven without having looked
at it first, right. Okay, so the גמרא *Gemara* says like this.
אמר רב אבוהו *Amar Rav Abbahu*, now that we mentioned a מיל
*mil* as a measure, we're going to talk about other mils also.
He said in the name of רבי שמעון בן לקיש *Rabbi Shimon
Ben Lakish*, רב אבוהו *Rav Abbahu* in the name of שמעון בן
לקיש *Shimon Ben Lakish*, so we're going to say a few other
things like that. Okay, אמר רב אבוהו אמר רבי שמעון לקיש *Amar
Rav Abbahu amar Rabbi Shimon Lakish*. So a similar statement of רב
אבוהו *Rav Abbahu* in the name of ריש לקיש *Resh Lakish*. לגבול
*Legabul*, when it comes to kneading dough, ולתפילה *u'letfilla* and for דאווענינג
*davening*, וליטילת ידים *u'li'netilat yadayim* and washing your hands, ארבעה מיל *arba'ah
mil*, four מיל *mil*. Now what does that mean? It means, so
רש"י *Rashi* says that kneading your dough, not a פסח *Pesach* concern,
it's a concern about you're kneading your dough בטהרה *betaharah*, kneading... you
make your dough בטהרה *betaharah*. Now you don't have any טהור *tahor*
vessels around. You're on a trip. This is sort of תוספות'ס *Tosafot's*
variation on רש"י *Rashi*. You're on a trip, you normally want to
eat your dough בטהרה *betaharah*, but you don't have any טהור *tahor*
vessels around. You know that for מיל *mil* ahead of you, like
a 72 minutes and, you know, an hour down the road, an
hour and a quarter down the road, you will find a baker
that does his dough בטהרה *betaharah*. So then you're supposed to wait
till you get there, because, you know, so wait an hour, it's
in the way you're going anyway. We'll talk about a minute if
you have to backtrack. If however it's longer than that, right? So
then you say, okay, so then you could, so then you can
go ahead and make your dough now, even though you won't make
it בטהרה *betaharah*, normally you make it בטהרה *betaharah*, we're not going
to insist that you go, you know, that you wait for forever
and then you can go ahead and you don't have to. But
if it's within ארבעה מיל *arba'ah mil*, you have to wait. That's
לגבול *legabul*. The other two are a little more relevant for us.
The other two are לתפילה *letfilla*. Now what does תפילה *tefilla* mean?
So רש"י *Rashi* says it means it's time for דאווענינג *davening*. But
and you're going into a city and basically the story is if
you have within ארבעה מיל *arba'ah mil* along your way within the
next, you know, whatever four kilometers, or here it was really also
in terms of time, not just distance, within the next hour you're
going to pass a שול *shul*, wait till you pass the שול
*shul*. Don't דאווען *daven* now. If you're not going to get to
a שול *shul* within the next hour or so, then you could
go ahead and דאווען *daven* now. Now it's interesting, רש"י *Rashi* mentions
a בית כנסת *beit knesset* by itself, as if there's significance of
דאווענינג *davening* in a בית כנסת *beit knesset*. He doesn't mention the
idea that there's a מנין *minyan*. When תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* paraphrases רש"י
*Rashi*, he says if there's a מנין *minyan*. So for תוספות *Tosafot*
the issue is if you could wait an hour and catch a
מנין *minyan*, wait the hour and catch a מנין *minyan*. Otherwise you
can go ahead and דאווען *daven* now. But for רש"י *Rashi* he
just mentions בית כנסת *beit knesset* as opposed to דאווענינג *davening* on
the side of the road. You know, that gets to issues in
גמרא *Gemara* in ברכות *Berachot* about דאווענינג *davening* on the side of
the road, waiting to go into, you know, maybe just the location
is significant. The final issue is נטילת ידים *netilat yadayim*. And this
does happen every time you're driving, right? You're taking your, you're driving,
you know, four hour, six hour car trip, you've packed sandwiches, and
what are you supposed to do about washing your hands? So if
you're smart, you pack some extra water ahead of time and then
you wash your hands, you do it off with the side of
the road or something. But otherwise it's like you're hungry, you want
to eat, but when's the next time you get a, hit a
rest stop that you can wash your hands? Do you have to
wait that long? So if it's within the next ארבעה מיל *arba'ah
mil*, then you have to wait to wash your hands before eating.
Would that matter business time now, I mean?
Well, presumably, presumably right, ארבעה מיל *arba'ah mil* would be four minutes.
Presumably it's a matter of time because it's not a question of
distance in per se, it's the amount of effort and postponement that
you have to do. Okay, but if it's more than that, then
you don't have to, then you don't have to wait. So the
גמרא *Gemara* says like this. אמר רב נחמן
בר יצחק *Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak*, איבו *Aivo* אמרה *amrah*, איבו
*Aivo* didn't say it, it was איבו *Aivo* who said it, not
רב אבוהו *Rav Abbahu*, it was איבו *Aivo*. וארבעה *V'arba'ah* אמר בה
*amar bah*. And he said four things, not three things. וחדא מנייהו
*V'chada mineihu*, so what was the fourth one? The one you didn't
mention was עיבוד *ibud*, working of leathers, which we mentioned actually just
a little, a little while ago. דתנן *Detnan*, because the הלכה *halacha*
is there's certain animals that, that the skin, the outer skin is
considered to be like the flesh of the animal, that it's considered
food, it's soft, it's edible, and it can become טמא *tamei*. Okay,
so other things, other animals like, you know, the hides, like I
don't know, think about an elephant or whatever, right, is obviously not
edible, so it's not food. Whereas other animals, the hide is edible
and therefore it is, unless you actually processed the hide and made
it into leather. So it says וכולן שעיבדן *vechullan she'ibedan*, all of
these hides of these animals that have soft hides, that normally it's
like the actual meat, if you actually treated them, או שהילך בהן
כדי עבודה *o shehilach bahen kedei avodah*, so either you treated them
in the various chemicals we discussed before, or you actually walked on
them the time it takes to do the processing. Because one way
in which they would
treat leathers, tan hides, would be a process of walking on them.
So if you walked on them that normal amount of time that
it takes to do the processing, טהורים *tehorim*, then they become considered
not like food, they become considered like hide, they're no longer meat-like,
they're more obviously like leather-like, and they are no longer can become
טמא *tamei*. חוץ מעור האדם *Chutz me'or ha'adam*. the exception of human
skin, which is very, I mean, you know, obviously this immediately makes
you think about the Nazi atrocities, you know, about what they do
with human skin. It’s so bizarre that the משנה *mishna* even mentions
this as an example of things that are being turned into leather.
If anybody says anything about that?
Yeah, I don't know. I don't know. Yeah, like why is it
even talking about it? Yeah, to be treating
it and so...
Right. Right.
There is a משנה *mishna* that discusses some case about using, you
know, after dead... you know, people who you would use the skins
and bones of dead bodies for,
you know, people that just died naturally and turn them into various
things. Wouldn't that be טמא *tamei* though by Jews? Not Jews. No.
Goyim too? Yeah, no, non-Jews or whatever. It was probably turning your
parents into a couch or something.
Right. Right. Right. Yeah, I don't know enough about if there's any
scholarship done about what the realities this is reflecting. Yeah, I know.
I know. Right. It's very hard to understand what reality this is
reflecting. וכמה כדי עבודה *Vekama kedei avoda*, how long is that time
to walk on the leather to that it becomes like leather? So
אמר רב יצחק *Amar Rav Yitzchak* or אמר רב אייבו *Amar Rav
Aivo*, אמר רבי ינאי *Amar Rabbi Yannai*, כדי הילוך ארבע מיל *Kedei
hiluch arba mil*, four מיל *mil*. So there's another issue of four
מיל *mil*. Okay, that was a little gruesome. אמר רבי יוסי ברבי
חנינא *Amar Rabbi Yose bar Rabbi Chanina*, לא שנו אלא לפניו *Lo
shanu ela lefanav*. So this is what I was telling you. That's
only if you have to wait and it's in the direction you're
going. ולאחריו *U'leachahrav*, let's say you pass the place. Let's say you
pass the town that had the שול *shul*. Or you pass the
rest stop that had the, you know, that you could have washed
your hands.
So אפילו מיל אינו חוזר *Afilu mil eino chozer*, then you don't
go by four מיל *mil*. If you have to backtrack, you don't
have to backtrack. Even a מיל *mil* you don't have to backtrack.
We're talking about waiting, but it's in the direction you're going. Backtrack,
that you don't have to do. Even a מיל *mil* you don't
have to. So the גמרא *Gemara* says we thought we were going
to get off easy, so the גמרא *Gemara* then says אמר רב
אחא ומינה *Amar Rav Acha u'minah*, from the fact that you said
even a מיל *mil* you don't have to backtrack, I can infer
מיל הוא דאינו חוזר *Mil hu de'eino chozer*, a מיל *mil* you
don't have to backtrack, הפחות ממיל חוזר *Ha'pachos mimil chozer*, anything less
you would have to backtrack. So if the only place to wash
your hands is less than a kilometer behind you, or assuming you
go by time, less than 18 minutes behind you, or there was
a שול *shul* that actually had a מנין *minyan* or something of
that sort, then you actually should backtrack if it is less than
one מיל *mil*'s distance. Okay, so that was an interesting little digression,
but this very important משנה *mishna* about if you don't determine חמץ
*chametz* by observation, you determine it by amount of time. Okay now,
another משנה *mishna* onto more obscure issues. Let's take a look. כיצד
מפרישים חלה בטומאה ביום טוב *Keitzad mafrishim challah be'tumah be'Yom Tov*? How
do you separate חלה *challah* בטומאה *be'tumah* on יום טוב Yom Tov
*Yom Tov*? What does it mean? You are טמא *tamei*, or the
חלה *challah* became טמא *tamei*. The dough you're dealing with. You're kneading
dough, you're making מצות *matzos*. Okay, it's יום טוב Yom Tov *Yom
Tov*, they would make מצות *matzos* on יום טוב Yom Tov *Yom
Tov*. They wouldn't do everything beforehand. Okay, you can bake on יום
טוב Yom Tov *Yom Tov*. Now, you're making so much dough, you
have to be מפריש *mafrish* חלה *challah*. What do you do when
you're מפריש *mafrish* the חלה *challah*? It's טמא *tamei*. So normally if
you have חלה טמאה *challah tmeiah*, not a problem. You have טמא
*tamei* dough, what do you do with טמא *tamei* dough? It's טמא
*tamei* חלה *challah*, you can't eat it, you burn it. Okay, but
there's a little bit of a problem. The problem is is that
if you leave it outside of the oven because to burn it,
it's going to become חמץ *chametz*. If you put it in the
oven, well it's יום טוב Yom Tov *Yom Tov*. You're not allowed
to bake things on יום טוב Yom Tov. *Yom Tov* that you're
not going to eat, and you're not allowed to eat חלה טמאה
*challah tmeiah*. Okay, what about leaving it outside of the oven and
burning it right away? No, because you're not allowed to burn, you
know, things on יום טוב Yom Tov *Yom Tov* either that you're
not getting any benefit from. Use
it for fuel. תוספות *Tosafot* has that discussion. You can't use it
for fuel because that's only an incidental benefit. When you burn חלה
טמאה *challah tmeiah*, it fundamentally is defined as the way תוספות *Tosafot*
says as an act of destruction, even if you're incidentally allowed to
benefit.
And therefore, what? For תרומה טמאה *Terumah Tmeiah* you can use it
for fuel?
Yeah, no, same point. But fundamental, you can't do it on יום
טוב Yom Tov. *Yom Tov* because it's fundamentally an act of destruction.
So you can't burn it because then you're doing a מלאכה Melacha
*melacha* not for food purposes, even though indirectly you might get benefit,
but you're not doing it. You can't bake it because you're not
going to be eating it. And you can't leave it without doing
anything to it. So what are you going to do with it?
You're stuck because it'll become חמץ *chametz*.
I'm sorry, so this חלה *challah* became טמא *tamei* somehow?
Yeah, the dough became טמא *tamei* and now you have to be
מפריש *mafrish* חלה *challah*. You know, that bug we were talking about
that fell into the עריבה *arevah* that touched the dough. Something happened,
it became טמא *tamei* and now you have to be מפריש *mafrish*
חלה *challah*. What are you going to do?
During the year, say regular, forget about פסח *Pesach*, like regular year.
You would be מפריש *mafrish* it and burn it.
You wouldn't give it to the כהן *kohen* because he can't have
it.
Yeah, unless it's חלת חוץ לארץ *challat chutz la'aretz*, and then כהנים
*kohanim* are allowed to eat, some כהנים *kohanim* are allowed to eat
חלת חוץ לארץ בטומאה *challat chutz la'aretz be'tumah*, but we're not going
to discuss that. רבי אליעזר אומר *Rabbi Eliezer omer*, so what do
you do? רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* says לא תקרא לה שם עד
שתאפה *lo tikra lah shem ad shete'afeh*. You don't, here's what you
do. Bake all the loaves of bread and don't be מפריש *mafrish*
חלה *challah* until after they're done baking. So while you're baking it,
nothing yet is חלה *challah*, right? And therefore you can bake it
all, because in theory I'm putting 20 loaves in the oven, I
can eat any one of those loaves. So after I bake it
all, and there's no... concern then take one of the loaves and
designate one of the loaves as חלה *challah*. Okay, that's a nice
trick. So you didn't bake it when it was already חלה *challah*.
You baked it when every single loaf was theoretically edible. Okay, that's
what you do. בן בתירה אומר *Ben Beteira omer*, בן בתירה *Ben
Beteira* says, תטיה בצונן *tateih betzonen*. Take the dough, don't bake it,
don't burn it, keep it in cold water till after יום טוב
Yom Tov. *Yom Tov*. And by keeping it in cold water, that'll
prevent fermentation, right? אמר רבי יהושע *Amar Rabbi Yehoshua*, imagine somebody doing
that nowadays, keeping dough outside of the oven on פסח *Pesach*. אמר
רבי יהושע *Amar Rabbi Yehoshua*, לא זהו חמץ שמוזהרין עליו בבל יראה
ובל ימצא *lo zehu chametz shemuzeharin alav beval yera'eh uval yimatzeh*. He
says, heck, you don't have to worry about it. It's חלה *challah*.
It's, so you don't transgress owning חלה *challah* that's, owning חלה *challah*
meaning the הלכה *halacha*, not חלה *challah*. You know, owning, owning חלה
*challah* that's תרומה *trumah* essentially. The חלה *challah* that goes to a
כהן *kohen*, you don't transgress. Why? It's sanctified, it's קודש *kodesh*, it's
not yours anymore, it goes to the כהנים *kohanim*, it's not any
particular כהן *kohen* yet, you haven't given it to the כהן *kohen*.
So nobody transgresses. Leave it around. אין לזה חמץ שמוזהרין עליו בבל
יראה ובל ימצא *Ein lezeh chametz shemuzeharin alav beval yera'eh uval yimatzeh*,
אלא מפרישה ומניחה עד הערב *ela mafrisha u'manicha ad ha'erev*. You separate
it and you leave it until the evening, you let it become
חמץ *chametz*. Who cares? Nobody's transgressing. Not yours, not the כהנים *kohanim's*.
ואם החמיצה החמיצה *V'im hechmitza hechmitza*, if it becomes חמץ *chametz*, גזונטהייט
*gesundheit*, what do I care? It seems pretty, again, a very casual
approach that, you know, we would not have to this. I don't
think we could imagine doing any of the last two suggestions. But
one is, but only one suggestion is you bake it. The other
is you put it in cold water, and the other is you
don't even care what happens to it, it's not yours. So by
the way, everybody, I assume you all know the ניגון *niggun* that
goes to this משנה *mishna*, right? צד מפריש חלה טוב *Tzad mafrish
challah tov*... Okay,
go ahead. I was singing it the whole day yesterday. Anyway, okay,
so moving on. All right.
It's the exact same number of syllables. Anyway, all right fine. So
the גמרא *Gemara* says like this. Try doing that once at a
wedding. Okay, so let's take a look at the גמרא *Gemara*. לימא
בטובת הנאה קמיפלגי *Leima betovat hana'ah kamiflagi*. What is this debate? That
last position that you don't own it seems to be a reasonable
position. It's sanctified, you can't eat it, a כהן *kohen* doesn't own
it yet. What's the debate? So let's say they debate whether טובת
הנאה tovah hana'ah *tovat hana'ah*, the benefit, the, the ability to get
benefit or is considered value. What that means is טובת הנאה *tovat
hana'ah* is a specific phrase which means this isn't yours, but you
have the ability to determine who gets it. You don't own this
חלה *challah*, but you have the right to choose which כהן *kohen*
gets it. Now, as anybody knows, right, you know that that's like
people that determine government contracts, that's a lot, you know, even if
you're not the recipient of the contract, if you get to choose
who gets it, especially if you're open to kickbacks, you know, that's,
that's worth a lot of money. So if you have the right
to determine who gets the חלה *challah*, even though it's not yours,
maybe that's considered an actual concrete benefit that you have that right,
and actually it's a, it's a benefit you have in the חלה
*challah* itself and therefore you actually have a degree of ownership in
the חלה *challah* because you actually have something at stake in the
חלה *challah*. You, you get to determine who gets it. So let's
say that's what the debate is, whether that makes it considered yours
or not. רבי אליעזר סבר טובת הנאה ממון *Rabbi Eliezer savar tovat
hana'ah mamon*. רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* holds that the idea that you
have the, the opportunity to determine who benefits from it, that is
considered a monetary ownership and therefore you do transgress בל יראה *bal
yera'eh* with this חלה *challah*. רבי יהושע סבר טובת הנאה אינה ממון
*Rabbi Yehoshua savar tovat hana'ah einah mamon*. It's not considered monetary, that
that right that you have, yes incidentally you'll get some benefit by
giving it to someone, by determining it, but you don't, it's not
really considered a monetary right or ownership that you have of the
object. And maybe that's the debate of whether you transgress or not.
So what about בן בתירה *Ben Beteira* then?
So he also would hold that it's considered to be ממון *mamon*,
meaning anybody that disagrees and says it's a problem of בל יראה
*bal yera'eh* would say your טובת הנאה *tovat hana'ah* is ממון *mamon*.
So the גמרא *Gemara* says, לא *lo*, not necessarily. דכולי עלמא סברי
טובת הנאה אינה ממון *De'kulei alma savri tovat hana'ah einah mamon*. Everybody
could hold it's not a monetary benefit. So why would then the
first opinion say it's a problem of owning it if it's not
really yours? והכא בהואיל קמיפלגי *Vehacha be'ho'il kamiflagi*. They debate the idea
of since, הואיל ho'il. *ho'il*, since, meaning hypothetically. רבי אליעזר סבר אמרינן
Amrinan הואיל ho'il ואי בעי מיתשיל עלה ממונא הוא *Rabbi Eliezer savar
amrinan ho'il v'i ba'ei mitshil alah mamona hu*. רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer*
says look, technically I agree, right now it's not yours, it's not
yet any particular כהן *kohen*. But since hypothetically you could always reverse
your taking of חלה *challah*, anything affected by a, a speech act
is considered like a נדר *neder* and you could always get it
retroactively annulled. So since hypothetically... yes, but you could always be מפריש
*mafrish* another piece, not this piece. So since hypothetically this could be
reversed, therefore ממונא הוא *mamona hu*, it's enough yours. It might not
be yours cause right now you have a benefit, but it's enough
yours cause you can still control its fate. You could always go
and get your vow annulled and re-take possession of this. And therefore
that enough makes it considered yours. That potential makes it enough considered
yours. רבי יהושע סבר לא אמרינן הואיל lo amrinan ho'il *Rabbi Yehoshua
savar lo amrinan ho'il*, we don't say that. I gotta tell you
of the two, it seems to me טובת הנאה *tovat hana'ah*... is
more of a good reason to consider to be your property than
this hypothetically you could reverse it. But the reason the גמרא doesn't
want to lock itself in is that there's a more universal debate
in the גמרא whether טובת הנאה this opportunity to direct it is
considered monetary ownership and it doesn't want to lock itself into that
debate. So it says in theory they could actually say it's not
and still it's considered yours because you could always reverse the status
here. Okay but that's one issue which is whether it is considered
to be the last opinion that he says you don't even transgress
if you own it and the answer is yeah you own it
enough or hypothetically you own it and therefore it's enough of a
problem. Now now we have another very key discussion about יום טוב
Yom Tov. which is very central to יום טוב Yom Tov. issues
about cooking on יום טוב Yom Tov. and we're going to circle
back around to what goes on in our משנה. Let's take a
look. איתמר Itmar it was taught האופה מיום טוב לחול ha'ofeh miyom
tov lechol you bake on יום טוב Yom Tov and you explicitly
say I'm doing it for tomorrow. Okay so you bake on יום
טוב Yom Tov. for non-יום טוב. Yom Tov רב חסדא אמר לוקי
Rav Chisda amar lokei רב חסדא Rav Chisda says you get lashes.
The תורה Torah only allowed you to cook and bake on יום
טוב Yom Tov for the purpose of יום טוב. Yom Tov רבה
אמר אין לוקי Rabbah amar ein lokei רבה Rabbah says you don't
get lashes. Now רב חסדא אמר לוקי Rav Chisda amar lokei you
get lashes why לא אמרינן הואיל ho'il. this is a different הואיל.
We don't say since ומיקלעי אורחי חזי ליה umikle'i orchei chazei lei
we don't look right now what's in your mind is you're baking
it and cooking it for after יום טוב. Yom Tov So therefore
it's not a cooking for the sake of יום טוב. Yom Tov
The counter argument is
hypothetically you could be for benefit of יום טוב. Yom Tov Even
if in your mind you were planning on doing it for Tuesday
whatever today is today is Sunday you're doing it for Tuesday if
people dropped by and you had all this food already cooked they
could eat from it. So objectively speaking not what you were intending
but objectively speaking this cooked food could be of benefit on יום
טוב. Yom Tov It was cooked today it could in theory be
eaten today and therefore it's not a I'm not saying it's so
kosher what you did but it's not a blatant violation because it
is cooking for the sake of יום טוב Yom Tov in the
sense that you could benefit from it on יום טוב. Yom Tov
Is that a function of time? Yes I'll talk about that in
a minute. That's what but he says רב חסדא Rav Chisda says
I don't buy that I don't say since guests could drop by.
רבה אמר אין לוקי Rabbah amar ein lokei you don't get lashes.
אמרינן we say הואיל yes since guests could drop by objectively you
could benefit from it on יום טוב Yom Tov even if you
didn't intend it and therefore it is considered for the sake of
יום טוב Yom Tov because it could be benefited. Now Michael asked
what if you cooked a minute before יום טוב Yom Tov. was
over right? So you would now or
places where people aren't really going to come by
well I don't think it matters if people weren't going to come
by but it does matter if the time might matter. תוספות says
that if you did it the last minute of יום טוב Yom
Tov and there was no time left to benefit from it on
יום טוב Yom Tov then רבה Rabbah would probably agree to רב
חסדא. Rav Chisda. Okay and said that you would but if there
just happened to be that you lived on a farm and there
was no one around for miles I don't think that would make
a difference because the point is is that right now you have
cooked food on יום טוב Yom Tov which you could eat right?
It is edible on יום טוב Yom Tov seems to be רבה's
Rabbah's point. But if there's no time on יום טוב Yom Tov
you know that might be a different story. Anyway that's רבה's Rabbah's
position. Okay so אמר ליה רבה לרב חסדא amar lei Rabbah leRav
Chisda so רבה Rabbah said to רב חסדא Rav Chisda לדידך דאמרת
לא אמרינן הואיל lidedach demart lo amrinan ho'il
according to you that we don't say since you have to actually
intend for it to be used on יום טוב Yom Tov הי
אופי מיום טוב לשבת hei ofei miyom tov leShabbat how do you
bake from יום טוב Yom Tov on שבת Shabbat right? We know
we make an עירובי תבשילין eruvei tavshilin we cook from יום טוב
Yom Tov. to שבת Shabbat says how you allowed to do it?
You're cooking for non-יום טוב. Yom Tov Okay and according to you
that's a violation. All right אמר ליה amar lei he said back
to him fine אמר ליה amar lei משום עירובי תבשילין mishum eruvei
tavshilin oh that's not a problem you made an עירוב. eruv. So
he said משום עירובי תבשילין שרינן איסורא דאורייתא mishum eruvei tavshilin shareinan
issura de'oraita what type of answer is that? If you're saying you
biblically transgress how does making an עירובי תבשילין eruvei tavshilin stop it
from being a biblical violation? אמר ליה amar lei, he said back
to him no אלא כדאמר רב יצחק ela kede'amar Rav Yitzchak מדאורייתא
צרכי שבת נעשין ביום טוב mi de'oraita tsorkhei Shabbat na'asin beyom tov
biblically speaking the same way you can cook on יום טוב Yom
Tov for יום טוב Yom Tov you can cook on יום טוב
Yom Tov for שבת Shabbat certainly if no certainly if they are
they are contiguous days then it is like one big קדושת יום
טוב kedushas Yom Tov it's a longer יום טוב Yom Tov, so
you're cooking on יום טוב Yom Tov for the יום טוב Yom
Tov, which includes the שבת Shabbat that follows. You probably can't cook
on a Sunday יום טוב Yom Tov for the following
שבת Shabbat the same way you can't cook on פסח for סוכות
Sukkot okay but you can cook on a on a contiguous שבת
Shabbat that all is considered it's an extension of the יום טוב.
Yom Tov, מדאורייתא צרכי שבת נעשין ביום טוב. mi de'oraita tsorkhei Shabbat
na'asin beyom tov. דרבנן הוא דגזרו בה derabbanan hu degazru bah the
Rabbis said don't do it from יום טוב Yom Tov to שבת
Shabbat because you'll start doing גזירה שמא יאמרו אופין מיום טוב אף
לחול gezeira shema yomru ofin miyom tov af lechol they'll think if
you can cook from יום טוב Yom Tov to שבת Shabbat you
can cook from יום טוב Yom Tov to the weekday. So they
said don't do it. And so therefore וכיון דאצריכו רבנן עירובי תבשילין
vekeivan de'atsrichu rabbanan eruvei tavshilin and then what the Rabbis did to
create a workaround for their own safe for their own prohibition is
they said... make an עירוב תבשילין, Eiruv Tavshilin, אית ליה היכירא, is
lei hekeira, then you're making something special, a sign, and everybody knows,
oh normally, right? That's what it says to people. It even says
to you, I have to make an עירוב תבשילין Eiruv Tavshilin or
I'm not allowed to do it. So it sends you the message
that you're not allowed to cook from יום טוב Yom Tov till
after יום טוב, Yom Tov, because I had to make an עירוב
תבשילין, Eiruv Tavshilin, and then it tells you, oh, and I can
only do it when it's שבת Shabbos and when I make an
עירוב תבשילין. Eiruv Tavshilin. So because we demand that, it's clear that
as a general rule, you can't cook from יום טוב Yom Tov,
till after יום טוב, Yom Tov, and that solves the problem. But
his basic answer is, how is it allowed? Isn't it a biblical
violation? His answer is no, because it's שבת, Shabbos, that makes a
difference. יום טוב Yom Tov, and שבת Shabbos are like one קדושה.
kedusha. That's different. But what I was saying is יום טוב לחול,
Yom Tov le'chol, that would be a biblical violation.
Okay, so he tries again. איתיבי, Aisivei, I'll ask you, says רבה,
Rabbah,
בהמה המסוכנת. behema hamesukenes. If you have an animal that is, you
know, sick, it's about to die. Now, it's not a טרפה. treifa.
A טרפה treifa is only an internal injury or what or some
type of a tear. This is an animal that's just dying of
old age. Now, if you wait till after יום טוב, Yom Tov.
it'll die and it'll be a נבילה, neveila, it'll be worthless. So
you want to שחט shacht it before it dies. Okay, so לא
ישחוט אלא כדי שיאכל הימנה כזית צלי מבעוד יום. Lo yishchot ela
k'dei sheyochal heimena k'zayis tzali mib'od yom. The only way you can
שחט shacht it on יום טוב is if there's enough time that
you could שחט shacht it and take a little piece, a כזית,
and put it and roast it and eat it before the day
is over. Why do we say roasting? Because roasting is the fastest
way to prepare. Also, you don't have to כשר kasher the meat
if you roast it because the blood drips away as opposed to
having to go through the process of salting. So basically, if you
want to שחט shacht your animal so it doesn't go to waste,
you can only do that if there's enough time to eat a
כזית of it before the day is over. Again, see that it's
an issue of time, that if there's no time, you've got a
problem. Okay, so רבה Rabbah says, יאכל, yochal, look, you see that
it's enough that there's theoretically enough time to eat a little bit
of its meat אף על גב דלא בעי למיכל, af al gav
delo bei l'meichal, even though you're not intending to actually eat the
meat of the animal. As long as theoretically there's time, that's enough.
בשלמא לדידי, Bishlama ledidi, it works according to me, דאמרי הואיל, de'amri
ho'il, that I say הואיל. הואיל ואי בעי למיכל מצי אכיל. Ho'il
v'ei bei l'meichal matzi achil. Since in theory, if you wanted to
eat the meat, you would have time to eat at least a
little bit of the meat roasted, so משום הכי ישחוט, mishum hachi
yishchot, so you can שחט shacht it because in theory it's able
to, you know, it's edible on יום טוב even if in practice
you're not going to do it.
אלא לדידך, Ela ledidach, you that say it goes by your subjective
intention, דאמרת לא אמרינן הואיל, de'amarta lo amrinan ho'il, we don't say
since, we don't say theoretically it's edible, we say you actually have
to want, be planning on eating it, אמאי ישחוט, amai yishchot, why
can you שחט? shacht? You're not planning on eating it. So אמר
ליה, amar lei, he said back to him, משום הפסד ממון. mishum
hefsed mamon. No, we let you do it so this whole big
thousand dollar animal doesn't go to waste. So he says again, ומשום
הפסד ממון שרינן איסור דאורייתא? Umishum hefsed mamon sharina issur d'oraissa? I
don't get it. You said it's a biblical prohibition. So just because
you don't want to lose a thousand dollar animal, we let you
do this? So אמר ליה, אין, yes, משום הפסד ממון, mishum hefsed
mamon, because
since the alternative is your thousand dollar cow is going to go
to waste, so therefore we let you do it. And what do
we let you do? We let you do it and גמר בליבו
לאכול כזית gamar belibo le'echol kezayis and ואי אפשר לכזית בשר בלא
שחיטה. v'ei efshar l'chezayis basar belo shechita. Basically, what we tell you
is like this. We will let you שחט shacht your animal if
you actually are planning on eating some of it today. And therefore,
even though it was the furthest thing from your mind to eat
this, if this is what's going to let you save your animal,
then you'll שחט shacht your animal and you'll really plan on eating
it today. And since in order to eat a כזית you have
to שחט shacht the whole animal, it allows you to שחט shacht
the whole animal. So his basic answer is, yes, in this case
I will say that we are going to, that we have allowed
it and what we've and but on the condition that you are
really planning on doing it. And since you know that that's what
you need to do in order to be able to eat, you
really will subjectively plan to do it.
So he got around an איסור דאורייתא. issur d'oraissa.
Got around an איסור דאורייתא issur d'oraissa by to
save money.
To save money. But by navigating the principles. Right.
Yes, you see, when they want to, they found an
איסור דאורייתא, issur d'oraissa, they found their path through it. They didn't
overwrite it, but they found their path through it. So this is
the debate which is very critical. We'll continue tomorrow. Again, רבה Rabbah
says you can cook on יום טוב or שחט shacht on יום
טוב even if you're not going to eat from it because as
long as the food is edible and fit to be eaten on
יום טוב, that means that it's considered for the צורך יום טוב.
tzorech Yom Tov. Whereas who's the other one? רב יוסף. Rav Yosef.
Who was the other one? Was it רב יוסף? Rav Yosef?
Who was? Whoever the other one was said רב חסדא, Rav Chisda,
thank you. רב חסדא Rav Chisda says no, it's only considered צורך
יום טוב tzorech Yom Tov if you're planning on eating it for
יום טוב, if that's your intention. And with the exception that if
it's for שבת, Shabbos, that's all the same, and in some cases
you'll make it your intention because you have to make it your
intention. But again, if it really isn't your intention... So we will
see tomorrow how this ties into our משנה. So the one... we
caught up, I want to make sure. Yes. So what does he
say? What does רבה Rabbah say? רבה Rabbah says since it's possible
for guests to come, you can bake it for them, so it's
considered צורך יום טוב Sorech Yom Tov even if you're really intending
it for the day after. Even if you're intending it for Sunday
on a Friday יום טוב, even without עירוב תבשילין. Eruv Tavshilin. If
you had no עירוב תבשילין, Eruv Tavshilin, as long as it's theoretically
edible, it is permissible. It's not the actual violation because the work
itself was theoretically permissible for that day. So that's the view of
רבה. Rabbah. Then we have the view of רב חסדא. Rav Chisda.
And רב חסדא Rav Chisda says no, it's only considered צורך יום
טוב Sorech Yom Tov if you're planning on eating it for יום
טוב, if that's your intention, and as with the exception that if
it's for שבת, Shabbos, that's all the same, and in some cases
you'll make it your intention because you have to make it your
intention, but again,
if it really isn't your intention,
according to him, that's not enough that it's theoretically edible, it's not
considered צורך יום טוב Sorech Yom Tov and you actually would violate
a מלאכה on יום טוב.